Finding Aid for Dept. of Physics (University of Michigan) publications 1915-ongoing
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Dept. of Physics (University of Michigan) publications 1915-[ongoing] 1988-1998
University of Michigan. Dept. of Physics.
0130 Bimu C26 2
1 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
Accessioned from the Department of Physics (Donor no. 1332 )
The records are open for research.
The first course in physics at the University of Michigan, entitled "Natural Philosophy," was taught in the Fall of 1843 by George Palmer Williams, Professor of Natural Philosophy and Mathematics. A Professor of Physics and Civil Engineering, Alexander Winchell, was appointed in January 1854. The first full Professor of Physics, James Craig Watson, was named in 1860.
The department began to take shape after the Physics Building (later called the West Physics Building and now known as West Hall) was built in 1888. Prior to that, at most one professor of physics existed at a time and classes took place in the North College or University Hall. Between 1890 and 1900, several instructors, assistant professors, and junior professors were appointed to the department.
Early interest in infrared spectroscopy, led by Harrison M. Randall in 1911, brought Michigan to the forefront as a research facility in physics. In the 1950s, research into infrared spectroscopy led to discovery of the principles behind fiber optics. Beginning in 1921, R.A. Sawyer and O.S. Duffendack accomplished substantial research in visible and ultraviolet spectroscopy. In 1932 discoveries by Dennison, Uhlenbeck, Cleeton, and Williams marked the beginning of microwave spectroscopy.
From 1915 to 1925 the department realized the need for systematization and interpretation of the large numbers of experiments being done. W.F. Colby consulted with researchers and led courses in theoretical physics to fill this need, thus beginning the Theoretical Physics program. The Summer Symposia in Physics began modestly in 1923. By 1928 its focus changed to Theoretical Physics and it became national and international in scope. Lecturers included P.A.M. Dirac, Enrico Fermi, Werner Heisenberg, Wolfgang Pauli, Neils Bohr, J.R. Oppenhiemer, H.A. Bethe, and Kasimir Fajans.
Since the 1920s the Applied Physics program has worked with other departments and research units toward practical applications of physics. Examples include an alliance with industrial organizations to reduce noise in automobiles, and a partnership with the Medical School to detect infrared measurements of amino acids.
The Nuclear Physics program was developed in the 1930s, led by the interest of Michigan theorists. Harrison M. Randall consulted with other programs at the University of California and the California Institute of Technology, as well as prominent physicists such as Enrico Fermi, when forming the program. The department hosted the Summer Symposia on Nuclear Physics in 1931 and later years to build international interest. In 1936 the department built a 36-inch cyclotron with the cooperation of the Medical School and with generous support from the Rackham Trust Fund. It was used for physics experiments as well as for medical research in leukemia and polycythemia. In 1939 the cyclotron was converted to 42 inches, and in 1962 it was replaced by an 83-inch cyclotron. In the 1970s the cyclotron was phased out due to federal cuts in nuclear research funding. Michigan gained prominence in accelerator development when the world's first electron synchrotron was built by the department beginning in 1946.
After World War II, interest developed in high energy physics. The department stood strongly in the area of particle detectors, most notably in the Nobel Prize-winning development by Donald Glaser of the Bubble Chamber in the 1950s.
As the department grew, it acquired new buildings. In 1923-24, the East Physics Building (now Randall Laboratory) was built for advanced research. In 1962-63, the ten-story Physics-Astronomy Building (Now the Dennison Building) was built to house the Physics-Astronomy Library, classrooms, and laboratories.
This history was excerpted from Zorn, J., ed. On the History of Physics at Michigan. Ann Arbor: Department of Physics, 1988. The Physics Department is planning to place this publication on their website: http://www.physics.lsa.umich.edu
Chairs of the University of Michigan Department of Physics
1911-1915 Karl E. Guthe (Director of the Physical Laboratory)
1915-1941 Harrison M. Randall
1941-1955 Ernest F. Barker
1955-1965 David Dennison
1965-1972 H. Richard Crane
1972-1977 Daniel Sinclair
1977-1982 Richard H. Sands
1982-1987 Lawrence W. Jones
1987-1992 Homer A. Neal
1992-1994 John F. Ward (Interim Chair)
1994-2004 Citrad Uher
2004-present Myron Campbell
The Department of Physics Publications are divided into three series: Unit Publications, Sub-Unit Publications, and Topical Publications. The Unit Publications series contains printed material published specifically by the Department of Physics. These publications are defined as being widely distributed and may be published at regular intervals. They are arranged by genre of the publication. The Sub-Unit Publications series contains publications from subordinate offices, departments, programs and organizations within the Department of Physics. These publications are arranged alphabetically by the creating sub-unit.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Dept. of Physics.; Physics--Study and teaching (Higher)--Curriculum.
Contributors:
University of Michigan Division of Atomic, Molecular and Optical Physics.
Genre/Form:
Reports.; Newsletters.; Pamphlets.; Bulletins.; Calendars.; Directories.; Histories.; Prospectuses.
- Unit Publications
  The Unit Publications series includes brochures describing graduate studies in the department dating from 1975 to 1987; bulletins announcing course offerings with the earliest dated 1915; calendars dating from 1992 to 1996 which announce events, conferences, and lectures being offered by the department; and directories. In 1996 the department ceased to publish a printed weekly calendar and created an e-mail list for the announcement of departmental events. These are printed out and found under the heading "Calendars (e-mail)" under the title Seminars and Colloquia. There are also several flyers describing individual colloquia, course announcements, lectures, and seminars. Many of these printed e-mail messages date from the late 1990s to the present.
  This series also contains a history of the department entitled On the History of Physics at Michigan: The Department of Physics, 1843- 1975 by Charles Meyer, George Lindsay, Ernest Barker, David Dennison, and Jens Zorn. This volume, published in 1988, also includes a study entitled Nuclear Physics at Michigan by William Parkinson. These two histories were written to celebrate the centennial of the first building devoted to physics research and teaching constructed on the University of Michigan campus. There is also an undated history entitled Physics and the Department of Physics Since 1900 by David M. Dennison.
  There are three newsletters included in the Unit Publications series. The Department of Physics Newsletter was published from 1988 to 1993 and continued until 1998 under the new title Michigan Physics Newsletter. A newsletter for alumni entitled News of Michigan Physics was published from 1978 to 1995. A copy of the 1988 prospectus entitled Prospectus for a New Physics Laboratory Building and Renovation of the Randall Laboratory Building is located in this series. There is also a 1991 report with an overview of the Department of Physics describing the long-range plans of the department. Several speeches given by Homer Neal are also in this series.
  - Biographies
    - Sir Gordon Birms Black McIvor Sutherland, 1907-1980, undated (Box 1)
  - Brochures
    - General 1968-1987, undated (Box 1)
    - Cyclotron Laboratory, undated (Box 1)
    - Description of Research Programs, undated (Box 1)
    - Graduate Studies in Physics, 1958, undated (Box 1)
    - Physics, 1956-1988 (Box 1)
  - Bulletins
    - Announcement of the Courses in Physics, 1915 (Box 1)
    - Applied Physics Program, undated (Box 1)
    - Graduate Studies, 1956/57, 1975, undated (Box 1)
    - Information for Physics Majors, 1977, undated (Box 1)
    - Physics at Michigan, undated (Box 1)
  - Calendars
    - [Department of Physics Calendar] 1995-1996, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Physics Department General Colloquia for Fall 1995, 1995 (Box 1)
    - This Week in Physics, 1992-1995, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Calendars (printed e-mail)
    - Seminar and Colloquium, 1996-2001, 5 folders (Box 1)
  - Directories
    - Faculty Research Activities
      - 1992 (Box 1)
      - 1993 (Box 1)
    - Physics Dept.
      - 1993-1994 (Box 1)
  - Flyers
    - Colloquia (printed e-mail)
      - Math Colloquium, 1999 (Box 1)
      - Physics Colloquium, 1998 (Box 1)
    - Course Announcements
      - The Physics of Complexity, 2001 (Box 1)
    - Invitations
      - Groundbreaking Ceremony and Reception, 1993 (Box 1)
    - Lectures
      - Saturday Morning Physics, 1998, undated (Box 1)
    - Lectures (printed e-mail)
      - Saturday Morning Physics, 1998-1999 (Box 1)
    - Seminars (printed e-mail)
      - Applied Physics, 1993 (Box 1)
      - Astrophysics Seminar, 2001 (Box 1)
      - Condensed Matter Seminar, 1997-2001 (Box 1)
      - High Energy Theory Seminar, 2000 (Box 1)
      - Particle Theory Seminar, 1996 (Box 1)
      - Physics Career Seminar, 2000 (Box 1)
      - Space Science, 1999-2001, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - Special Seminars, 1996-1999 (Box 1)
      - Spin Physics Seminar, 2000 (Box 1)
  - Histories
    - On the History of Physics at Michigan: The Department of Physics, 1843-1975 by Charles Meyer et al. includes Nuclear Physics at Michigan by William C. Parkinson, 1988 (Box 1)
    - Physics and the Department of Physics Since 1900 by David M. Dennison, undated (Box 1)
  - Invitations 1990 (Box 1)
  - Manuals
    - Physics Department Information Guide, undated (Box 1)
  - Newsletters
    - Department of Physics Newsletter, vol. 1-5, 1988-1993, 5 folders (Box 1)
    - Michigan Physics Newsletter, vol. 1-10, 1993-1998, 5 folders (Box 1)
    - News of Michigan Physics, no. 1-15, 1978-1995, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Proposals
    - A Proposal to the U.S. Atomic Energy Commission for the Construction of an 83" Spiral-Pole Cyclotron, January 1958 (Box 1)
  - Prospectus
    - Prospectus for a New Physics Laboratory Building and Renovation of the Randall Laboratory Building, 1988 (Box 1)
  - Reports
    - Overview and Long Range Plan, Version 1.01, 1990 (Box 1)
    - Overview and Long Range Plan, Version 1.02, 1991 (Box 1)
    - Physics Faculty Research Summaries, 1991 (Box 1)
    - Present Status of Space Planning, 1988 (Box 1)
  - Speeches by Homer Neal 1990 (Box 1)
- Sub-Unit Publications
  The Sub-Unit Publications series includes a 1996 flyer describing a symposium sponsored by the Division of Atomic, Molecular and Optical Physics.
  - Division of Atomic, Molecular and Optical Physics
    - Flyers 1996 (Box 1)
- Topical Publications
  The Topical Publications series includes printed materials published to document specific events or activities such as fund-raising or special lectures hosted by the Department of Physics. The Topical Publications include flyers and programs describing the H.R. Crane Lectures and Symposium, the Samuel A. Goudsmit Lecture Series, and the Ta-You Wu Lectures. These scattered announcements date from 1988 to 1998. There is also a flyer announcing the Rev. Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr. Symposium held in 1996 and a single bulletin describing the course offerings for the 1939 Summer Session.
  - H. R. Crane Lecture
    - Programs 1988-1989 (Box 1)
  - H. R. Crane Symposium
    - Flyers (printed e-mail) 1997 (Box 1)
  - Rev. Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr. Symposium
    - Flyers 1996 (Box 1)
  - Samuel A. Goudsmit Lecture Series
    - Flyers 1990-1992 (Box 1)
    - Programs 1989-1990 (Box 1)
  - Summer Session
    - Bulletins
      - Physics, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Ta-You Wu Lecture
    - Flyers 1993-1998, undated (Box 1)